Good day, today's daf is נ"ז nun zayin 57. We're in the
middle of a whole discussion of שבע מצוות בני נח. Sheva Mitzvos
Bnei Noach.
We pick up in תנא דבי מנשה,
Tana
D'bei Menashe, I guess we'll pick up from there about 10 lines
from the bottom on נ"ו עמוד ב', nun vav amud bet, 4,
5, 6, 7, 8, 9 lines from the bottom. And what we
had done is first we had a whole
discussion, first of all we saw that some people have add some
or have some different מצוות mitzvos from the classic. The classic again
is the big three: עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, גילוי עריות, Giluy Arayos,
שפיכות דמים, Shfichus Damim, and then א' ב' ג' ד': alef bet
gimmel dalet: אבר מן החי, Ever Min Hachay, ברכת השם, Birchas Hashem,
גזל, Gezel, and דינים. Dinim. All of those are actually initially learned
from פסוקים pesukim about אדם, Adam, not just limited to נח. Noach.
Then we had actually an opinion that said one minute there's other
things maybe in stead or in addition, particularly was mentioned סירוס, sirus,
which was sterilizing,
castrating animals and humans, and כלאים, kilayim, mixing seeds, well actually not
mixing seeds, mixing trees and mixing crossbreeding animals. And we pointed out
that both of those two are very rooted also in בראשית, Bereishit,
in the פרו ורבו peru u'revu and in the למיניהו. l'mineihu. And
the גמרא Gemara most recently said that this opinion תנא דבי מנשה
Tana D'bei Menashe would actually substitute these two for ברכת השם Birchas
Hashem and דינים, Dinim, would not actually have those two, which was
interesting. And then of course there's another category of כישוף kishuf of
witchcraft. And the other thing we saw was a whole discussion about
whether דינים Dinim was added to בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael at מרה,
Marah, which would be explain why if you don't have דינים Dinim
in this list, but interestingly for us the point was
that it was an exploration of what's included in דינים. Dinim. And
included in דינים Dinim seems to be first of all the setting
up of a court system, courts in every town, in every region
and so on. But also consistent with רמב"ן's Ramban approach, we said
רמב"ם Rambam just fits it to a court system, רמב"ן's Ramban approach
is it seems to be substantive law. It's learned from the פסוק
pasuk about למען אשר יצוה את בניו ואת ביתו אחריו ושמרו דרך
ה' לעשות צדקה ומשפט, l'maan asher yetzaveh et banav v'et beito acharav
v'shamru derech Hashem la'asot tzedakah u'mishpat, to do righteousness and justice. Of
course you might want to say that means to enforce those laws,
but it seems to create a system of laws. And in particular,
the גמרא Gemara did discuss whether דינים Dinim would whether קנסות knassos
would be included. Because a קנס knas the way רש"י Rashi says
it's really about צדקה ומשפט, tzedakah u'mishpat, it really isn't about righting
a wrong and it really isn't about like compensation and sort of
like those aspects of civil law, it's going beyond that, it's fining
and so on. But that certainly seems like דינים Dinim includes substantive
civil law that's about creating a just society and that's obviously very
important if it includes that entire idea. And the other final thing
we mentioned, which is going to be a recurring theme today, is
that the way in which it's adjudicated in a Jewish court is
different than in a non-Jewish court and the little sort of distillation
of that is עדה, עדים והתראה. edah, edim, v'hasra'ah. עדה edah means
what we learn out עדה edah and עדה edah is 20 plus
3, whatever, a בית דין beit din of 23, there they can
have even one judge, so there's no formal size of the court.
עדים, edim, we need two witnesses, they do not need two witnesses,
maybe even hearsay or whatever circumstantial evidence, and התראה, hasra'ah, we need
warning and they adjudicate even without warning. Okay, so that's a nice
distillation of those differences. Now we pick up from the actually we
can start from the word האי תנא, Hai Tana, of the word
תנא, Tana, it is nine lines from the bottom on נ"ו עמוד
ב'. nun vav amud bet. האי תנא דבי מנשה הוא. Hai Tana
b'dei Menashe hu. So the one who says דינים Dinim came later
with בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael at מרה Marah is the תנא דבי
מנשה, Tana D'bei Menashe, דמפיק ד"ח ומעייל ס"כ. d'mappik dach v'ayel sach.
Takes out דינים Dinim and ברכת השם Birchas Hashem and puts in
ס"כ, sach, סירוס וכלאים. sirus v'kilayim. דתנא דבי מנשה, D'tana D'bei Menashe,
like of course we talk from the house of מנשה, Menashe, שבע
מצוות נצטוו בני נח: Sheva mitzvos nitztavu Bnei Noach: עבודה זרה, גילוי
עריות, ושפיכות דמים, Avodah Zarah, Giluy Arayos, Shfichus Damim, the classic three,
גזל ואבר מן החי Gezel v'Ever Min Hachay and now instead of
דינים Dinim and ברכת השם, Birchas Hashem, סירוס וכלאים, sirus v'kilayim,
sterilizing and crossbreeding. רבי יהודה אומר אדם הראשון לא נצטוה אלא עבודה
זרה בלבד. Rabbi Yehuda omer Adam HaRishon lo nitztaveh ela Avodah Zarah
bilvad. So here's a radical opinion, אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon was only
given עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. Now, he might not
disagree, רש"י Rashi says maybe he gets other מצוות mitzvos by נח,
Noach, but don't root them all in אדם הראשון. Adam HaRishon. Don't
try to say all seven came from אדם הראשון. Adam HaRishon. אדם
הראשון Adam HaRishon only got עבודה זרה בלבד. Avodah Zarah bilvad. שנאמר
ויצו ה' אלהים על האדם. Shene'emar vayetzav Hashem Elokim al HaAdam. God
commanded the human, so obviously מצוה mitzvah of not eating from the
עץ הדעת etz hadaat is not for future generations, but the concept
that's for future generations is that there is a God who is
a commander. ויצו ה' אלהים. Vayetzav Hashem Elokim. So the idea of
belief and acceptance of God and not worshiping עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah,
that is a central theme to that whole story of גן עדן,
Gan Eden, that was the basic obligation to the first humans. Any
more came maybe later, came at
נח. Noach. רבי יהודה בן בתירה אומר Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer
says a similar approach but... broadening it a little bit. אף על
ברכת השם, Af al birchat Hashem, not just about not worshipping עבודה
זרה, Avodah Zarah, but not cursing God, right? If part of the
idea is accepting and recognizing God, it’s also not,
if you’re attacking God, that is also going against that core theological
principle on which the world was sort of founded. Okay, so ברכת
השם Birchat Hashem would be included. ויש אומרים אף על הדינים, Veyesh
omrim af al hadinim, and some say even on a system of
laws. Okay, so we’ll see how that works in. כמאן אזלא הא
דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Keman azla ha de’amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav, who is it going like this teaching in the name of
רב? Rav? אלהים אני, Elohim ani, it’s as if God said to
the humans, ויצו ה' אלהים, Vayetzav Hashem Elohim, know that I am
your God, right? ה' אלהים. Hashem Elohim. לא תקללוני, Lo tekaleluni,
do not curse me, accept me as your God. אלהים אני לא
תמירוני, Elohim ani lo temiruni,
do not replace me with some other god, do not worship עבודה
זרה. Avodah Zarah. אלהים אני יהא מוראי עליכם, Elohim ani yehei morai
aleichem, I am your God, let my fear be on you. So
what’s the third one coming to include? כמאן כהני דאמרי, Keman kehani
de’amri, that’s coming to include the idea of דינים. dinim. Now how
does the idea of fear of God include the idea of דינים?
dinim? So what רש"י Rashi says it means is the idea like,
לא תטה משפט כי המשפט לאלהים הוא, Lo tateh mishpat ki hamishpat
le’Elohim hu,
that it’s like if you have to judge justly, then you have
to be more afraid of God than you are afraid of human
beings. If you’re afraid of human beings, you’ll pervert the justice because
you don’t want to upset people and so on. If the only
thing that
you have to answer to is God and you’re truly afraid of
God, you’ll judge truly, you’ll judge justly. The problem with that is,
is that that emphasizes the God, assuming you already understand the responsibility
to judge. And the God part is just making sure that you
do it justly. It’s not, רש"י Rashi doesn’t really explain how from
the God concept you derive a responsibility to judge, right? Which is
what this, so what I would sort of more rather say is,
if
you believe in what type of God are you believing in? Right,
if you’re a Greek and you believe in multiple gods and you
believe,
one of the main differences of course between the Jewish idea of
God
and the pagan idea, besides the question of one or many, is
that pagan
gods are amoral, meaning not immoral but amoral, right? They don’t represent
an absolute moral
code. The Jewish concept of God
is a God who is, who there’s a single truth, חותמו של
הקדוש ברוך הוא אמת, Chotamo shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu emet, and God
represents a single true morality that we’re bound by. So if that’s
bound up in the concept of God,
so therefore if my fear is upon you, that means that you
are going to understand a responsibility to
create society and rule society in a way that it becomes a
moral and a just society. So what I’m trying to say is
that you can get the idea of דינים, dinim, but it requires
that your idea of God include an idea of morality and justice.
But if that’s your idea of God and then you have that
fear of God, you understand that responsibility, that that’s how society should
be structured, you’re going to have a just society. Anyway, according to
this, the first humans were not commanded in the things
that were more particular. They were commanded in these basic universal principles
of belief in God, that’s a universal religious principle, not cursing God,
which is bound up in that, and according to this, a just
society. That, by the way, very much connects to the פסוק pasuk
by אברהם, Avraham, right? ושמרו דרך ה'. Veshamru derech Hashem. What’s דרך
ה'? Derech Hashem? לעשות צדקה ומשפט. La’asot tzedakah umishpat. So there’s something
like very powerful about saying that the most basic foundation, before you
get to נח, Noach, before you get to אבר מן החי, Ever
min hachai, or even נגזל nigzal sort of wrapped up in it,
you know, but before you get to something like
גילוי עריות, Giluy arayot, the basic idea is that accepting God and
accepting that that means like
דינים, dinim, like being responsible for creating a just society. That, if
talking about like Mendelssohn’s idea of like natural law, you know, that
obviously could be very much in sync with that. So these are
these approaches that that’s what אדם הראשון Adam Harishon was commanded. Now
this does not deny that נח Noach was commanded more. By נח
Noach you get explicitly murder, the spilling of blood, eating an animal
with its soul in it, with the blood of the soul still
in it, and so on. But אדם הראשון, Adam Harishon, let’s not
put all seven on אדם הראשון. Adam Harishon. אדם הראשון Adam Harishon
are these foundational ones. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, תנא
דבי מנשה. Tana d’vei Menashe. Now we’ve talked about, now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, תנא דבי מנשה. Tana d’vei Menashe. Now let’s
talk about בני מנשה Bnei Menashe that doesn’t have ברכת השם Birchat
Hashem and דינים dinim and instead has סירוס וכלאים, Sirus vechilayim, right?
It replaces these two
with these two. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara wants to say, how
are you going to get that from the פסוקים? psukim? where are
you going to get סירוס Seirus and כלאים Kilayim from the פסוקים
psukim and take out those two, okay, according to the approach that
we learned it all from the פסוק pasuk by אדם הראשון? Adam
HaRishon? So it says like this: תנא דבי מנשה. Tanna d'vei Menashe.
אי דריש ויצו, Ei darish vayetzav, if they learn it from that
פסוק pasuk by אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon ויצו, vayetzav, so in that
case אפילו הנך נמי, afilu hanach nami, so they should have included
ברכת השם Birchas Hashem and דינים. Dinim. אי לא דריש ויצו, Ei
lo darish vayetzav, and if he doesn't base it on that פסוק
pasuk by אדם הראשון, Adam HaRishon, הני מנא ליה? hani mana lei?
So where do you know any of these? Okay, and certainly things
like גזל Gezel and אבר מן החי Ever Min HaChai or whatever.
So how is it that you get this list? Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says לעולם לא דריש ויצו. Le'olam lo darish vayetzav. So
now we're going to have a really interesting thing. Forget the ויצו
Vayetzav פסוק. pasuk. We already suggested one approach that basically says forget
the ויצו Vayetzav פסוק, pasuk, it's only a basic idea of God
and you know, believing in God and not cursing God and creating
דינים Dinim maybe. Here also we're going to say forget the ויצו
Vayetzav פסוק, pasuk, that is not the basis of the שבע מצוות.
Sheva Mitzvos. הני, Hani, so where does בני מנשה B'nei Menashe get
seven מצוות? mitzvos? הני כל חדא וחדא באפי נפשה כתיבי. Hani kol
chada vechada be'apei nafsha ketivi. They're going to, he's going to learn
it out individually, but interestingly, if you're going to pay attention, the
way תנא דבי מנשה Tanna d'vei Menashe is going to learn it
out from is from no מצוות mitzvos by אדם הראשון. Adam HaRishon.
He's going to learn them all out from נח. Noach. So I
think there's a really important conceptual question here, right, whether שבע מצוות
בני נח Sheva Mitzvos B'nei Noach were said to אדם, Adam, were
they said to נח, Noach, or were they said in like two
stages, right? And why is that different? Like who cares? So it's
a difference of ten generations, it's still said to all humanity. Well
the difference is, is that נח Noach was sort of like, you
know, after the human did sin, the world was destroyed and so
on. So do you understand the idea that like in theory the
world could have existed had everybody done the right thing, I mean
what does that mean because we're humans, but anyway, could have existed
with like just one basic idea: God. Believe in God. Or maybe
work to create a just society. But because we, you know, made
so many mistakes and ותשחת הארץ vatishachet ha'aretz and the world had
to be destroyed or whatever, then we needed more direction and we
needed more מצוות. mitzvos. And then we kept on making mistakes and
then we needed a lot more direction and then we had the
613 מצוות mitzvos for ישראל, Yisrael, right? So that's sort of like
a way of understanding the whole arch of ספר בראשית Sefer Bereishis
is we keep on messing up and therefore we need more and
more instruction and direction, we can't be trusted to just, you know,
to our own devices. But it's interesting here, right, how much do
you think that these שבע מצוות Sheva Mitzvos all started with אדם,
Adam, or how much do you think אדם Adam was basically the
God idea, maybe דינים Dinim idea, and the rest started with נח.
Noach. So here בני מנשה B'nei Menashe is, תנא דבי מנשה Tanna
d'vei Menashe is going to make all seven linked to בני נח
B'nei Noach and not to אדם Adam or נח. Noach. So let's
take a look. כל חדא וחדא באפי נפשה כתיבא. Kol chada vechada
be'apei nafsha ketiva. עבודה זרה וגילוי עריות. Avodah Zarah veGiluy Arayos. עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah and גילוי עריות, Giluy Arayos, דכתיב: dechativ: ותשחת הארץ
לפני האלוהים. Vatishachet ha'aretz lifnei Ha'elokim. So this is top of נז
עמוד א. nun-zayin amud aleph. The land was corrupted before God. ותנא
דבי רבי ישמעאל, VeTanna d'vei Rabbi Yishmael, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael teaches:
כל מקום שנאמר השחתה אינו אלא דבר ערווה ועבודת כוכבים. Kol makom
shene'emar hashchasa eino ela dvar ervah va'avodas kochavim. To corrupt means, means
sexual sin and idolatry. דבר ערווה Dvar ervah שנאמר: shene'emar: כי
השחית כל בשר את דרכו על הארץ. ki hishchis kol basar es
darko al ha'aretz.
All the flesh corrupted its way on the land. Now of course
that's similar to the first פסוק. pasuk. How does that show that
it's about sexual sin? So רש"י Rashi says the word דרך derech
means like its natural way of being and maybe also the word
בשר basar emphasizes like, you know, a certain fleshiness, you know, so
a certain corporal aspect to it. So it means its way of
sexuality, corrupted sort of the natural sexual, you know, way in which,
in which animals sort of, you know, exert, you know,
exhibit their sexuality, so you know, cross-breeding and other types of sexual
sin. So somehow that's associated with that word
השחתה. hashchasa. ועבודת כוכבים Va'avodas kochavim and idolatry דכתיב: dechativ: פן תשחיתון
ועשיתם לכם פסל תמונת כל סמל, pen tishchitun va'asisem lachem pesel tmunas
kol samel, lest you act corruptly and you make for yourself some
type of an image. So the word תשחית tishchis is a word
that means idolatry and sexual sin. Now this doesn't show you where
they're commanded. It shows you that they're being punished. But it's inferred,
if they're being punished for these things, then clearly they were commanded
not to do them. Okay, that's at least the logic of the
rabbis that you know, every punishment requires a warning and a commandment.
Yes, so he says even in the issue of קין, Kayin, like
how would he know?
Right, and how did God hold קין Kayin responsible?
Right, so well I think that's an interesting question, right, you know,
according to like why is God holding קין Kayin responsible?
And, and you know, is, um, I mean I have a whole
it's not even a דבר תורה dvar Torah it's a whole דרך
derech in understanding the whole thing, but the, I guess I'll say
it in one, it ruins it to say it in one sentence,
but anyway, but I will say the following: what's fascinating is as
according to the idea that humans were commanded in murder, you know,
based on the פסוק pasuk by אברהם, Abraham, by אברהם, Abraham, by
אדם, Adam,
okay, then קין Kayin could be held responsible because he was commanded.
But if but if but if it's only was only commanded in
it later, right, how can they be held responsible? So חז״ל *Chazal*
certainly are understanding like the same way it infers from the fact
that they're being punished for sexual sin they must have been commanded,
חז״ל *Chazal* would presumably say we can infer from the fact that
קין *Kayin* was punished that he was commanded, although interestingly that's not
the argument that's going to be made. We're going to see that
the argument about murder is based on a different פסוק pasuk! *pasuk*,
a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that comes after קין *Kayin*, a פסוק pasuk,
*pasuk* that comes after the flood. So it never, it's a good
question, it never goes back and says wait, but if the if
the murder was only commanded after the flood, right, and how can
you assume that if there's punishment there was commandedness, whatever happened to
קין *Kayin*? He was punished without being commanded. So that's a really
good question. I mean I would say that by the way, and
this is not just my own approach, like I once heard like
the basic approach like this from a Doctor David Shatz, and it's
all based on an understanding of what the first sin was. Now
we're getting to a whole big thing so I'm going to I'm
going to say it in one sentence, but the first big sin,
you know, by the whole by the whole עץ הדעת טוב ורע
*Etz HaDaat Tov VaRa*, what was that sin about? Was it just
about an arbitrary command and defying God's authority, you know, like that's,
you know, but what is it about עץ הדעת טוב ורע *Etz
HaDaat Tov VaRa*? So a approach, it's already sort of Hirsch says
something similar, but this philosopher Michael Wyschogrod says it in a very
nice way, in a very clear way. He says that the basic
sin was what's לדעת טוב ורע *laDaat Tov VaRa*. לדעת טוב ורע
*laDaat Tov VaRa* is who gets
to whose moral judgment is determines, meaning it's not a question of
will you just obey God? You know, I can trust, you know,
you that what I know that something I'm doing is wrong and
choose to do it anyway. I can know it's wrong to go
smoking or whatever, to smoke or to go drink, but I can
do it anyway, right? But it's a very different when I say
I actually don't accept that it's wrong, I think it's right. So
the sin of לדעת *laDaat* of the עץ הדעת טוב ורע *Etz
HaDaat Tov VaRa* was not אדם Adam *Adam* and חוה *Chavah* saying
like we don't we're not going to listen to God. It's saying
we're not going to trust God in terms of what's good and
bad. We're going to decide for ourselves what's right and what's wrong.
So if that was the sin, right, and now I have to
now that I'm saying this I have to say the whole thing
or parts of it anyway. So it's very interesting, right, because God,
right, וירא אלקים כי טוב *VaYar Elokim Ki Tov*. God creates and
then God determines that something is good,
right? So God knows what's טוב *tov* and what's רע *ra*. And
the human being therefore, according to this, their sin is that they
want to be the ones to determine it. So when חוה *Chavah*
eats from the tree it says as opposed to וירא אלקים כי
טוב *VaYar Elokim Ki Tov*, it says ותרא האשה כי טוב העץ
למאכל *VaTere HaIshah Ki Tov
HaEtz LMaachal*. She's deciding that it's good. Anyway, so if you understand
that, then the aftermath of the eating from the tree is God
is saying, oh, you want to decide what's good and bad? Then
you go ahead and you figure it out for yourselves and you'll
be held
accountable. So therefore, you know, קין *Kayin* can't say, oh, nobody told
me it was wrong. Like listen, that was what you accepted. You
wanted to be like, you wanted to figure it out for yourselves,
you wanted to, you know, so you're going to be held accountable
for that whether I've told you or not. And then the whole
story of the rest of בראשית Bereishis, *Breishit* ultimately leading up to
הר סיני *Har Sinai* is getting back into that relationship where we're
working together with God and God is giving us direction but we're
still partners in it whatever. So now I just did the whole
thing, the whole brilliant דבר תורה *dvar Torah* in two minutes. What?
חמר מדינה *Chamar Medinas* versus זילמנוביץ *Zilmanovitz*.
Exactly. And the whole process is like do we get to be
adults and think for ourselves but also be in a relationship with
God and trust God's judgment and how does that work out? So
that was my whole מהלך *mahalach* through all of ספר בראשית *Sefer
Breishit* and half of שמות *Shmot* in two minutes. But anyway, but
it was a good question. Okay, so
so you're right. Meaning according to חז״ל *Chazal*, the sense you get
here is not that way. The sense you get is also a
little bit the רמב״ם *Rambam* and Mendelssohn, how much is it commandedness
and how much is it natural law that we could figure out
ourselves? The sense you get here is is that it would not
have been the שבע מצות *sheva mitzvot*, they wouldn't have been punished
had they not been commanded, and that it's not just that they're
left to figure it out for themselves. Yes.
This is why they say earlier that אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon *Adam
HaRishon* was a מין min, *min*.
Oh, because like he separated himself.
Right right right. He wanted his own, that's a good point, tying
into that word yet to that whole point about מנהו *minhu*. Okay,
so anyway now that עבודה זרה Avoda Zara, *avodah zarah* itself like
a whole approach to יידישקייט *yiddishkeit* in the world, but moving on.
Okay, השחית כל בשר את דרכו *hishchit kol basar es darko*, עבודת
כוכבים *avodas kochavim*, דכתיב d'chsiv *deksiv* פן תשחיתון ועשיתם *pen tashchisun vaasisem*.
Okay, so that's how you get those two. ואידך V'idach, *veidach*, now
if you say that you learned it out from אדם הראשון Adam
HaRishon *Adam HaRishon*, what do you do by those פסוקים psukim, *psukim*
by נח Noach, *Noach*? Aren't they telling that to you? No, אורחיה
דקמגלי *orchayu dekamagli*,
the Torah is revealing what the people did that they sinned, but
that's not the source of how it's forbidden. The source of how
it's forbidden is אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon *Adam HaRishon*. שפיכות דמים Shfichus
Damim *shfichus damim*, דכתיב *deksiv*, how do you know murder? שופך דם
האדם באדם דמו ישפך Shofech dam ha'adam ba'adam damo yishafach. *shofech dam
haadam baadam damo yishafach*, right? That's clear. That's one of the few
things explicitly commanded to נח Noach, *Noach*, that it's deserving of death.
So that's where it's clearly being commanded. Again, interesting. not being inferred
from the Cain story. ואידך, v'idach, what would the other one say
who said it had already been commanded? קטליה הוא דקא מגלי. Katlei
hu d'ka megalei. No, the Torah is telling you what the punishment
is. Okay, we already knew it was forbidden to murder from Adam,
but here it's telling you the punishment is באדם דמו ישפך, ba'adam
damo yishafach, that you'll get executed. Okay, גזל, gezel, where do we
know גזל? gezel? Again from Noah, דכתיב כי ירק עשב נתתי לכם
את הכל. ki yerek esev nasati lachem es hakol. I have given
you the flesh of the animals like the grass of the ground,
okay, which means that at the same way grass grows wild, okay,
and obviously there's no stealing, you can have whatever is like, you
know, wild and ownerless, but you cannot take stuff that belongs to
somebody else. Okay, ואמר רב לוי V'amar Rav Levi כי ירק עשב
ולא כירק גינה, ki yerek esev v'lo k'yerek gina, like grass that
you know vegetation that grows like grass vegetation that grows wild, but
not vegetation of a garden, you know, not something that belongs to
somebody else. That's where you learn גזל. gezel. ואידך, V'idach,
it's interesting it doesn't learn it from the word חמס, chamas, right?
Because the word חמס chamas could mean violence, but according to חז"ל,
Chazal, חמס chamas also means violent taking of things that aren't yours.
Anyway, ואידך, V'idach... הוא למישרי בשר הוא דאתא. hu l'mishrei basar hu
d'asa.
That's coming to permit meat, right? The understanding is that אדם הראשון
Adam HaRishon, was only allowed to eat, you know, vegetation, because in
the פסוקים, psukim the initial פסוקים psukim in בראשית, it only says
I've given you, you know, the fruit of the trees etc. and
it doesn't say I've given you the flesh of the animals. And
here by Noah, it says that I've given you, you know, the
animals like the grass of the ground. So therefore, what it's coming
to do here is not to forbid stealing, but to permit Noah
to eat meat. Now what I'm waiting for somebody to ask, רש"י
Rashi asks, תוספות Tosafos asks, is one minute,
if it wasn't only permitted by Noah to eat meat, how do
you say that אדם Adam הראשון was commanded in אבר מן החי?
ever min hachai? Adam, you don't need to forbid אבר מן החי
ever min hachai if you're forbidden to eat meat altogether. So right,
so if the permission of meat only came later, why did you
need to forbid אבר מן החי? ever min hachai? Why not, you
know, all meat was forbidden. So the basic answer, any guesses what
the answer might be?
So the answer is אבר מן החי, ever min hachai, when we're
saying that אדם Adam, הראשון was forbidden to eat meat, it wasn't
that he had to be a vegetarian. It was that he wasn't
allowed to take animal life for the sake of eating meat. But
he was allowed to eat from the meat of animals that had
died naturally, okay? The prohibition was about taking animal life to serve
his needs. What? Not very safe. What can I tell you?
Anyway, so, so anyway, so therefore for that it was forbidden, the
same way it was forbidden to take animal life, it was forbidden
to rip a limb from a living animal. Afterwards, it was even
permitted to take animal life but still not to take an אבר
מן החי. ever min hachai. All right.
Yes, but it's still you're talking about a living. You're not allowed
to take.
You can't kill it! Maybe you could take a limb.
Okay.
Okay. אבר מן החי דכתיב, Ever min hachai d'chsiv, now how do
we know אבר מן החי? ever min hachai? Again, from Noah. This
whole approach learns it all from Noah. אך בשר בנפשו דמו לא
תאכלו. Ach basar b'nafsho damo lo socheilu. Now how do you get
that? I have to tell you, this just shows how I was
like, I'm like, you know, I've so been trained to think through
the lens of the rabbis. So the way the rabbis read it,
which רש"י Rashi on the פסוקים pesukim is אך בשר, ach basar,
when it comes to eating flesh, בנפשו דמו, b'nafsho damo, when the
blood and the life is still in the animal, don't eat the
flesh of the animal. Don't eat flesh when the animal's alive. So
anyway, I was once talking to my son and he said, 'Yeah,
you know, how in the Torah like it's you know Noah and
his family were forbidden to eat blood.' I said, 'What are you
talking about? Where's it say they were forbidden blood?' He says, 'What
are you talking about? It's the פסוק! pasuk, It says אך בשר,
ach basar, as far as flesh is concerned, בנפשו, b'nafsho, when the
flesh still has its life force and its blood in it, don't
eat the flesh.' Meaning, what do you have to do? You have
to take the blood out of the meat before you eat the
meat. The פשט, pshat, the simple פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk
is about not eating blood. Right? You can eat meat but don't
eat it with its life force and with the blood still in
it, right? It's prohibiting the blood which is by the way we
saw an opinion before that it was דם מן החי. dam min
hachai. Now rabbis say it means when the blood and the life
force is in the animal, don't eat the meat. But I think,
you know, I mean he didn't make it up, I think he
read it somewhere, but I think that that's a very reasonable simple
read of the פסוק, pasuk right? As far as flesh is concerned,
don't eat it while its blood, which is its life force, still
is in the meat. All right, but anyway, the rabbis read it
to be about אבר מן החי. ever min hachai. So with again
from Noah. ואידך, what would the other one say if אבר מן
החי ever min hachai was already prohibited to Adam? He would say
to you ההוא למשרי שרצים הוא דאתא. hahu l'mishrei shratzim hu d'asa.
Yes, that's coming to tell you don't eat meat that there's a
concept of blood and the soul being distinct from the flesh. But
for at least the rabbis understand when it comes to like rodents
or whatever we see the blood as a type of a flesh,
we don't see it as distinct, so for rodents like אבר מן
החי ever min hachai is not forbidden. forbidden because they're not seen
in this category of like a sort of if you will a
body soul dualism, a life force separate from the flesh. I can't
exactly explain why.
But halakhically the blood of rodents is considered like the meat of
rodents, it's not considered like blood. סירוס, Sirus, now where does he
learn out? So again, he's not learning out ברכת השם Birkhas Hashem
and דינים. Dinim. That's interesting. And it's I, you know, I gotta
tell you, it's a little strange, a little even in a little
ways disturbing that you know, to exclude, I mean ברכת השם Birkhas
Hashem you could say, you know, is maybe obviously somewhat of you've
got it covered by עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, but excluding דינים Dinim
it feels a little like you know, hard to understand what you
don't have a responsibility to broadly create a just society, just these
types of narrow things? But anyway, but he replaces them with these
two. And these two we already mentioned, although here he's focusing on
נח, Noach you know, these two are very much rooted in the
core aspects of creation, of פרו ורבו Pru U'rvu and למיניהו, Leminehu,
which is essentially what he's going to say. So it says like
this: סירוס דכתיב שרצו בארץ ורבו בה, Sirus d'chtiv Shirtzu ba'aretz u'rvu
vah, which is the command given to נח, Noach again, a type
of a פרו ורבו, Pru U'rvu, spread out in the land. ואידך
לברכה דעלמא, V'idach l'vircha d'alma, that's a blessing, that's not a command.
ואידך... okay, כלאים, Kilayim, cross-breeding, דכתיב מהעוף למיניהו, d'chtiv Meh-of l'minehu, the
same as a למיניהו l'minehu is in the act of creation when
you bring the birds into the ark, they're each one to their
own species. You have to keep the species distinct. ואידך ההוא לצוותא
דעלמא, V'idach hahu l'tzavsa d'alma, that's just to, you know, that they
should have like a friendship, companionship. So you have them with their
own מין, you know, they like to hang out with their own
kind, but it's not a prohibition of cross-breeding. The prohibition of cross-breeding
came actually according to this, there is no prohibition of cross-breeding. And
according to the standard approach, there's no prohibition of סירוס. Sirus. אמר
רב יוסף אמר בי רב על שלוש מצוות. Amar Rav Yosef amar
bei Rav al shalosh mitzvos. So now what do we have? We
have שבע מצוות Sheva Mitzvos given to אדם הראשון, the classic seven.
We have the idea, no, all seven were given basically in the
נח Noach, period, and that requires... comes with an interesting swap. So
it's two issues: one is נח Noach, versus אדם and the other's
what
are you swapping out? And it's a little funny to be swapping
out דינים, Dinim, but סירוס Sirus and כלאים Kilayim certainly speak to
some deep-rooted aspects of creation. Then we have an approach that אדם
got one, two or three, he got basically the idea of a
God and the idea of דינים, Dinim, and the rest maybe came
later at נח, Noach, splitting it up. And now we're going to
have yet another approach. Yes.
Would it be that it's the difference between some things that are
natural law that's so intuitive that you don't need a specific commandment?
I was thinking about that. Maybe you take out דינים Dinim because
דינים Dinim is natural law and therefore doesn't need to be commanded?
Sort of like a little פשרה pshara between Mendelssohn and Rambam, you
know. The ones that are commanded are more religious, certainly עבודה זרה,
Avoda Zara, you know, but it would still be funny that שפיכות
דמים Shfichus Damim is still one of the commanded ones, right, and
not one of the... doesn't exactly work, you know. So that's this
is the ongoing question also, right, the commandedness versus the universal natural
law aspect. Okay, so אמר רב יוסף אמר... Amar Rav Yosef amar...
okay, so now we're going to have a search only three מצוות.
mitzvos. Oh no, שלוש מצוות נהרג, shalosh mitzvos neherag, excuse me. Now
we're moving from what was he commanded to what is it punishable
by death. Anybody who's learned שבע מצוות בני נח Sheva Mitzvos B'nei
Noach before knows this general idea that oh, you know, they're liable
to the death penalty for any one of them, even if they
steal a פרוטה prutah or less than a פרוטה. prutah. But interestingly,
we're going to see that that is not universally accepted, that there's
some opinions that the death penalty is only for a very small
number of the שבע מצוות בני נח, Sheva Mitzvos B'nei Noach, small
not very small, there's only seven. Okay, but anyway. So אמר רב
יוסף אמר בי רב על שלוש מצוות בני נח נהרג. Amar Rav
Yosef amar bei Rav al shalosh mitzvos ben Noach neherag. He's only
executed for three of them. גשר, Gesher, and the ראשי תיבות rashei
teivos is גשר: Gesher: על גילוי עריות ועל שפיכות דמים ועל ברכת
השם. Al Gilluy Arayos v'al Shfichus Damim v'al Birkhas Hashem. Okay, so
that's an interesting three, especially since you don't have עבודה זרה, Avoda
Zara, you have ברכת השם Birkhas Hashem and not עבודה זרה, Avoda
Zara, right? If it was עבודה זרה, avoda zara. then it would
be the same three that for us are the cardinal three sins.
Okay, so מתקיף לה רב ששת
בשלמא שפיכות דמים דכתיב... maskif lah Rav Sheshes bishlama Shfichus Damim d'chtiv...
I get it... that's the most explicit one in the פסוק, pasuk
שופך דם האדם באדם דמו ישפך. I mean that's explicit. אלא הנך
מנלן? Ella hanach minalan? Where are the other two from? אי גמר
משפיכות דמים, I'gmar miShfichus Damim, if you say שפיכות דמים shefichos damim,
tells you it's punishable by death and now we're going to apply
it to the שבע מצוות בני נח, Sheva Mitzvos B'nei Noach, so
if that's true, אפילו כולהו נמי. afillu kulhu nami. So apply it
to all שבע מצוות בני נח. Sheva Mitzvos B'nei Noach. אם משום
דאיתרבי... Im shum d'israbey...
so that's one poss... so obviously it can't be a general application.
So where else are you going to get therefore גילוי עריות Gilluy
Arayos and ברכת השם? Birkhas Hashem? אם משום דאיתרבי מאיש איש... Im
shum d'israbey m'ish ish...
Okay, so here's an interesting possibility which gets back to what we
started this whole thing off with yesterday, right? Remember the פסוק says
by ברכת השם: Birkhas Hashem: איש איש כי יקלל אלוהיו,
Ish ish ki
yekalel elohav, right, ונשא חטאו, v'nasah cheto, and then it talks about
in the end רגום ירגמו, ragom yirgmu, right, רגום ירגמו. ragom yirgmu.
So איש איש ish ish we said according to one approach was
to include non-Jews. So that's the case of ברכת השם Birchas Hashem
איש איש. ish ish. Well, guess what, that's good. That's helping us
get like we're only going to apply the execution to a small
number. Murderers in the פסוקים by נח, Noach, here's by ברכת השם,
Birchas Hashem, and how do we get עריות? arayos? Because it says
by עריות: arayos: איש איש אל כל שאר בשרו לא
תקרבו לגלות ערוה,
ish ish el kol she'er besaro lo
tikrevu legalos ervah, לא תקרבו לגלות
ערוה,
lo tikrevu
legalos ervah, אני השם. ani Hashem. Okay, so
by עריות arayos and by ברכת השם, Birchas Hashem, you have איש
איש. ish ish. Okay, by the way, this is really fascinating what
the גמרא's Gemara going to get to when we turn the page,
which is what does it mean conceptually? Before, I said what does
it mean conceptually to have them all in אדם, or all by
נח, or to split it and see a progression. What does it
mean to say בני נח Bnei Noach were included basically when בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael were commanded and they were thrown into that category
there? Is that just revealing to us that they were always commanded
way back in נח, it's just hinting it to us here, right?
Or is this somehow, is it conceptually telling us somehow that their,
you know, they're included in some conceptual way together with this מצוה
mitzvah to ישראל? Yisrael? It's interesting, but here we're not saying that
we're learning that that's where they're commanded. What we're saying is we're
learning from here that this is, that their punishment is the death
penalty. Okay, and we learn it from a פסוק by ברכת השם
Birchas Hashem and a פסוק by גילוי עריות. gilluy arayos. That's how
we know those three the death penalty. So the גמרא Gemara says,
that's true, עבודת
כוכבים נמי, avodas kochavim nami, איתרבי israbi מאיש איש. mi-ish ish. It
says איש איש ish ish from עבודה זרה. avoda zara? What does
it say about עבודה זרה? avoda zara? I forget, רש"י Rashi tells
us.
What does it say about עבודה זרה? avoda zara. איש
איש מבני ישראל ומן
הגר הגר
בישראל אשר יתן מזרעו למולך,
ish ish mi-bnei Yisrael u-min ha-ger ha-gar
be-Yisrael asher yiten
mi-zar'o la-Molech, מות יומת. mos yumos. So it says איש איש אשר
יתן מזרעו למולך. ish ish asher yiten mi-zar'o la-Molech. So we also
have עבודה זרה. avoda zara, So it should be four. By the
way, that at least is nice. Then you have the three cardinal
sins: עבודה זרה, avoda zara, גילוי עריות, gilluy arayos, שפיכות דמים, and
ברכת השם Birchas Hashem which is, you know, an extension of עבודה
זרה, avoda zara? it's rejecting whatever God. Okay, so that would be
very nice. But it should be four. So אלא אמר רב ששת,
ella amar Rav Sheshes, הני אמרי בי רב, hanni amri bei Rav,
על ארבע
מצוות בן נח נהרג. al arba mitzvos ben Noach neherag. All right,
good! We'll make it those four. It's four out of seven. Okay,
fine. Now, that's okay, so that's a nice conceptual idea. They're נהרג
neherag on the cardinal ones which are also the ones that Jews
are נהרג neherag on—I mean, certain types of גילוי עריות. gilluy arayos.
Okay, and not on the ones that are not so cardinal, that
are not the cardinal ones. But now the גמרא's Gemara going to
double back and question this. דעבודת כוכבים בן נח נהרג? da-avodas kochavim
ben Noach neherag? Is it really true that a בן נח ben
Noach is executed for idolatry? והתניא, ve-hatanya, בברייתא: be-braisa: בעבודת כוכבים. be-avodas
kochavim. Now we're going to deal with ברייתות braisos that talk about
what is the scope of the שבע מצוות בני נח? sheva mitzvos
Bnei Noach? And how does that compare A, when they're interacting with
Jews, and how does that compare to what the Jews' liability is?
Okay, and I want to warn you that this entire next set
of text, the word we're going to be seeing now is not
גוי goy or בן נח ben Noach but כותי. Kusi. Because there's
going to be, you know, that's a signal, Samaritan, that it's going
to be offensive stuff or stuff that the Jews did not want
the non-Jews to have to see, okay, so sort of self-censored. And
even, it's interesting, even certain editions of the גמרא Gemara that have
like some of the correct stuff that was censored out—like you remember
a while ago we had the whole אגדתא agadata about קיסר Keisar
and it wasn't in our גמרא Gemara and it was like it
was in other גמרות. gemaros. At least some that I looked at,
even those גמרות gemaros that put back the stuff about Caesars still
keeps the word כותי Kusi in this text. So, get ready, here's
another trigger warning, I guess. Okay, so. אמרי בי
רב. amri bei Rav. So anyway, is it really true that a
בן נח ben Noach is executed by עבודה זרה? avodah zarah, והתניא,
ve-hatanya, תנא ברייתא: tana braisa:
בעבודת כוכבים, be-avodas kochavim, when it comes to the מצוה mitzvah of
the prohibition of idolatry for בני נח, Bnei Noach, דברים שבית דין
של ישראל ממיתין עליהם, devarim she-Beis Din shel Yisrael memisin aleihem, acts
of idolatry that a Jewish court would execute Jews for,
בן נח מוזהר עליהן. ben Noach muzhar aleihen. Meaning what? And we
discussed this yesterday. Like, so things like shows of adoration, hugging and
kissing that were not acts of worship, would not be included in
בני נח Bnei Noach because that would not be an act of
worship in a Jewish court. The other interesting question was how about
making an idol? Would that also be excluded from this? Okay, but
right now that's not our interest exactly, the scope. Our interest is
the phrase as it says, בן נח מוזהר. ben Noach muzhar. It
doesn't say—and logically it should have said "executed". Because it should have
said logically: דברים שבית דין של ישראל ממיתין עליהם, devarim she-Beis Din
shel Yisrael memisin aleihem, a things that a Jewish court would
execute, בן נח נהרג עליהן, ben Noach neherag aleihen, right? בן נח
ben Noach is executed. You just said ממיתין, memisin, right? So the
fact that you switched from a Jewish court executing to a בן
נח... ben Noach... All right, so אזהרה אין, azharah in, it's only
a prohibition, מיתה לא, mitah lo, it sounds like it's not the
death penalty. All right,
so אזהרה אין, azharah in, it's only a prohibition, מיתה לא, mitah
lo, it sounds like it's not a death penalty. So אמר רב
נחמן בר יצחק, amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, אזהרה שלהן זו היא
מיתתן. azharah shelahen zu hi mitatan. No, their warning, that is their
death penalty. Now what does that mean? So I will tell you
again, you know, when normally the way this phrase is interpreted in
like, you know, most a lot of rabbinic discourse, means that even
though the Torah never says to them, never says if you do
this you'll be punishable by death, you know, the fact that God
prohibited it means that it's deserving of death. Now why should that
be true more of them than of us? I'll get to in
a minute. But it's talk- when it's mi- but that's sort of
the normal way that that's understood. That could also be an explanation
of like, well what say they weren't, they weren't intentional, they were
שוגג? shogeg? Let's say they didn't have warning. No, אזהרה שלהן זו
היא מיתתן. azharah shelahen zu hi mitatan. Because we're going to find
out later that they might even be like even if they're שוגג,
shogeg, it's deserving of death. Very, very harsh. It says like, no,
you know, the fact that God warned it, that means you're deserving
of death, you know, the rest is all your responsibility. If you're
ignorant or whatever, it's not our fault. Okay, so it's very sort
of sense of this harshness. Now what's the logic behind that? The
logic behind that in some מפרשים meforshim basically say this about, you
know, Jews as well. They say, look, you know, if God, who
is the source of all life, tells you not to do something,
then as soon as you violate, you know, what God said, you
sort of have lost your sort of right for living, you know,
you've gone against, you know, you know, this is- you were given
your life by God and any sense of violation in a sense
is inservable, it- will- is punishable by death. It's only through God's,
you know, compassion that allows other lesser forms of punishment than the
one that ultimately really is deserved for any violation of God's will.
It's a pretty austere and harsh way of looking at the world.
You know, so, so
Rav Soloveitchik says, since we're in- getting- coming up to the ימים
נוראים Yamin Noraim period, you know, at the very end of the
יום כיפור Yom Kippur in the נעילה Neilah service, I think one
of the last things we say is something about save ourselves- what-
I'm trying to remember the line, but it's something basically, you know,
save ourselves מחמס ידינו, me-chamas yadeinu, from the חמס, chamas, from the
sort of again, could be violence but theft of our hands. So
he basically says why of all the things do we single that
out at the end of יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? So he says,
well, because in a way, any sin that we do means that
we're stealing from God, we're stealing our life from God, you know,
that we're sort of taking, because we have lost our right really,
you know, to, you know, to, you know, we're living, you know,
God's given us our life to follow God's מצוות, mitzvot, so in
a sense we're taking it away from God in a way when
we violate God's will. So anyway, I'm not sure you would say
this as harshly as deserving of death, I'd have to look at
it again, but still. Anyway, so this is one way of thinking
about this, which means, you know, really in principle any violation of
God's will, whether you're whether you're conscious- whether you're not, you know,
intentional or not intentional, whatever, is all deserving of death. Everything else
is just going easy on you. So by בני נח, Bnei Noach,
it's sort of left at this state. That's normally the way that
phrase is interpreted. However, it's not probably what the גמרא Gemara means
here because the גמרא Gemara here remember is working with the sense
that only four מצוות mitzvot are deserving of death, not all seven.
So it's not saying that philosophically any prohibition, any violation of God's
will is deserving of death. And רש"י Rashi says it does that
it's not making a sort of a philosophical or religious comment, it's
just making a textual point. When the ברייתא braita says they're warned
against עבודה זרה, avodah zarah the ברייתא braita means by saying warned,
it means that they're killed for it. It's Rashi- isn't being
specific. Okay, it says that they're warned against it, but it means
that that would be something they'd be executed for. It's just not
going into that level of detail. Okay, so that makes it much
more philosophical and just practical. Okay, so again, we're working with the
idea that there's only four מצוות בני נח mitzvot Bnei Noach is
killed on, the big three plus ברכת השם. Birkat Hashem. What do
you do by the fact that this ברייתא braita says that they're
warned by עבודה זרה avodah zarah, but it doesn't say they're killed?
So we say it doesn't mean that they're just warned. They are
killed. It's not being specific. אזהרה שלהן זו היא מיתתן. azharah shelahen
zu hi mitatan. When it says that they are warned, it means
that they're killed for it. We're not being
specific. רב הונא ורב יהודה וכולהו תלמידי דרב, Rav Huna ve-Rav Yehudah
ve-kulehu talmidei de-Rav, that's saying only four of the seven. Now all
these other students of רב, Rav, that was in the name of
רב Rav I believe, but all these other students of רב Rav
אמרי, amri, they said על שבע מצוות בני נח נהרג. al sheva
mitzvot Bnei Noach neherag. Nope, for all seven. Okay, and that's normally
the way we, you know, what gets said. Okay, גלי רחמנא בחדא,
gali rachmana be-chada, the Torah reveals it by one of them, by
murder, it says explicitly, והוא הדין לכולהו, ve-hu ha-din le-kulehu, all the
מצוות mitzvot is deserving of the death penalty. Okay, now that's very
harsh. You steal a penny and you're deserving of the death penalty,
right? And that's where that phrase אזהרה שלהן זו היא מיתתן azharah
shelahen zu hi mitatan gets evoked. Yes, in principle any violation of
God's will is deserving of death. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says ועל גזל בן נח נהרג? ve-al gezel ben noach neherag? Now
that we've said all seven, so before we questioned עבודה זרה, but
now we're going to question the others. Really? Executed by all of
these, even by theft?
והתניא, ve-hatanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, על
הגזל. al ha-gezel. גנב, Ganav, whether it's burglary, וגזל, vegazel, or theft,
וכן יפת תואר, vechen yefat to'ar, or taking a captive woman in
war, right, that's a type of a theft which is interesting, right,
it's a type of adultery if she's married, but it's also a
type of a theft. You're kidnapping her, you're stealing her away from
her husband, you're stealing her away from her family. Okay, that would
be included even though it's in a war context. וכן כיוצא בהן
vechen kayotze bahen and any similar types of things are also included
in theft. So what's similar? The גמרא Gemara will get to. But
now we go on and this is talking about Jew versus non-Jew.
This is the trigger warning. Okay, כותי בכותי, Kuti b'Kuti, again now
it says כותי, Kuti, but anyway, גוי בגוי, goy b'goy, okay, a
Gentile who steals from a Gentile,
וגוי בישראל, vegoy b'Yisrael, or a Gentile who steals from a Jew,
אסור, assur, that's all included in the שבע מצוות בני נח. Sheva
Mitzvot Bnei Noach. ישראל בגוי, Yisrael b'goy, however, a ישראל Yisrael and
implicitly a ישראל Yisrael who steals from a ישראל Yisrael is אסור,
assur, but a ישראל בגוי, Yisrael b'goy, מותר, mutar, that's permissible. Not
only, right, which is a whole question about whether גזל גוי gezel
goy is מותר mutar or not, is it allowed to steal from
a non-Jew. Now if you look at the ראשונים, Rishonim, their גרסא
girsa is always גזל גוי gezel goy by here and by other
cases, but if you look in the גמרא Gemara in בבא קמא
Bava Kamma that discusses it, the גמרא Gemara discusses whether not even
גזל גוי gezel goy is permissible, and not even גזל כותי, gezel
Kuti, but it's גזל כנעני. gezel Kna'ani. It's always this euphemism, God
forbid we're talking about anybody who's lived for the last three thousand
years, we're talking about these Canaanites, okay, but this is really a
question about גזל גוי. gezel goy. Alright, so anyway, so we'll get
back to this in a minute, but for now our focus is
on why does it say אסור assur when it's talking about a
Gentile stealing from a Gentile or from a Jew, that it says
that it is אסור? assur? It doesn't say that it is liable
the death penalty. ואי איתא, ve-ee ita, so why does it say
אסור? assur? נתני חייב, nitni chayav, that you're liable in the sense
that there's a punishment, okay. The fact that it just says forbidden
doesn't sound like it's something punishable by death. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, משום דקבעי למתני סיפא mishum d'ka ba'ei lemitni seifa because
we want to say in the end ישראל בכותי, Yisrael b'Kuti, or
whatever, בגוי, b'goy, מותר. mutar. So since we wanted to say מותר,
mutar, the contrast word to מותר mutar isn't חייב, chayav, the contrast
word to מותר mutar is אסור. assur. So when we said forbidden,
yes, forbidden and deserving of death, but we said forbidden because we
were contrasting it to the word that's permissible, okay, דתנא רישא אסור.
d'tanna reisha assur. Alright, so now of course the funny thing is
that do we really mean it's totally permissible? So, you know, so
רש"י Rashi says, I mean, you know, some say that not stealing
from a non-Jew is אסור assur because of דרבנן, derabbanan, some say
it's אסור, assur, you know, דאורייתא, de'oraita, some say it's דרבנן. derabbanan.
רש"י Rashi says the author of this ברייתא braisa feels that it's
totally מותר, mutar, which is quite shocking. In בבא קמא Bava Kamma
at least he says, well, as long as there's no חילול השם
Chillul Hashem involved, okay, but anyway, but bracketing חילול השם Chillul Hashem
concerns, it's totally permissible. So if you want to say מותר mutar
by this, then you're going to say אסור assur by the non-Jew
rather than saying חייב. chayav. So the reality is that by the
case of the שבע מצוות Sheva Mitzvot it is חייב, chayav, but
we said אסור assur to contrast it to מותר. mutar. Again, very
difficult גמרא Gemara around this aspect of stealing from a non-Jew. But
wait, it's going to get worse, okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
והא כל היכא
דאיכא
חיובא מיתני קתני. veha kol heicha d'ika chiyuva mitni katani. Wait
a minute, והא כל היכא דאיכא חיובא מיתני קתני. veha kol heicha
d'ika chiyuva mitni katani. But that's not true, you can't say it
says אסור assur even though it really means deserving of the death
penalty, that there's a real liability, because when there's a real punishment,
it says it explicitly. Where does it say it explicitly? דתניא רישא,
detanya reisha, the beginning of the ברייתא braisa says על שפיכות דמים,
al shefichut damim, what's the story about murder? What's the scope of
that? כותי בכותי Kuti b'Kuti וכותי בישראל, v'Kuti b'Yisrael, or whatever, גוי
בגוי, goy b'goy, a Gentile and a Gentile or a Gentile killing
a Jew, חייב. chayav. That's a violation of the שבע מצוות Sheva
Mitzvot and they're not אסור assur but חייב. chayav. So it means
deserving of the right presumably of the death penalty. ישראל בכותי, Yisrael
b'Kuti, פטור. patur. So it doesn't say מותר mutar at least, it
says פטור, patur, is exempt. Okay,
so anyway, this is obviously very disturbing about what do we say
about this issue, right, about murder of a non-Jew, of a Gentile,
even though it here it says כותי. Kuti. So רמב"ם Rambam actually,
it's very interesting, in the text of the רמב"ם, Rambam, רמבם Rambam
opens up the הלכות רוצח ושמירת נפש Hilchot Rotzeach u'Shmirat Nefesh says
כל ההורג נפש kol hahoreg nefesh הרי זה עובר, harei zeh over,
you know, with the איסור issur of לא תרצח. lo tirtzach. Anybody
who executes, who murders somebody, transgresses you shall not murder. And then
it's a question about whether you, whether who gets the death penalty.
So maybe a Jew doesn't get a death penalty for killing a
non-Jew, but it's still is considered fundamentally murder, it's a question about
whether they get the death penalty or not. Okay, even that's a
question about what does that distinction show, but at least it's being
included in the prohibition of murder, it's just a question of whether
they get executed or not. The question though is some say that
that was actually an edited version of the רמב"ם, Rambam, and that
the original text of the רמב"ם Rambam read כל ההורג נפש מישראל
kol hahoreg nefesh miYisrael עובר בלא תרצח. over b'lo tirtzach. So it
raises really deep questions about what do we say about, you know,
it's clear we say that you don't get the death penalty, a
Jew killing a
non-, you know,
killing a non-Jew. What do we say about persecuted and murdered by
the non-Jews, so you can understand some of the context, but still,
it's obviously deeply disturbing. Anyway, for our purposes, what it's saying is
look, it says when a non-Jew murders, חייב. chayav. So clearly when
it wants to say חייב, chayav, it says חייב. chayav. So by
גזל, gezel, which is deserving of the death penalty, it should have
said חייב chayav and it shouldn't just have said אסור. assur. So
let's just read the answer. So the answer is התם היכי ליתני?
hasam heichi lisni?
What should it teach? ליתני אסור ומותר? lisni assur umutar? Should it
say, oh, no, cause I'm telling you that it's לאו דווקא. lav
davka. It'll say אסור assur even when it means חייב. chayav. But
it can't say אסור assur by the case of murder, because if
it would have said אסור assur by the non-Jew, it would have
had to have said מותר mutar by the Jew, and that we
do not want to say. We don't want to say that it's
מותר. mutar. והתניא, vehatanya, כותי, Kuti, again it's גוי, goy, ורועה בהמה
דקה vero'eh behema daka and shepherd, לא מעלין ולא מורידין. lo maalin
velo moridin. You don't take them out of the well if they
fell down, but you don't throw them in the well either. You're
not supposed to kill them. So we're not going to say מותר.
mutar. So since for a Jew vis-a-vis a non-Jew, you have to
say אסור, assur, so then you're going to be explicit by a
non-Jew and say חייב. chayav. Okay, but חייב, chayav, so some, so
sometimes we'll be explicit and say חייב chayav and sometimes we'll say
אסור, assur, but אסור assur can also mean חייב. chayav. And therefore
when we're talking about גזל, gezel, even though it says אסור, assur,
it really means חייב. chayav. So what we're asserting now is it
could be all שבע מצוות sheva mitzvos are deserving of the death
penalty. And even though in this ברייתא braita sometimes it says חייב
chayav and sometimes it says אסור, assur, it really, it's all equal.
It's all deserving of the death penalty. It's all equally liable. Yes.
You got a question.
Probably not going to go into this. Probably not.
But okay, yes. No, but so okay, like we
read it with all the politically correct qualifications on the side. But
thousands of other people read the same thing right now. Right. And
then how is
it
taught?
Right. That is the big problem. I mean, when people write, look,
you know, רבקה Rivka עליה השלום, aleha hashalom, I don't know you,
you know she was, used to be a regular of the דף
היומי Daf Yomi and very sharp, you know, feminist. The other thing
that she was very מקפיד makpid on when we came up with
a דף daf was anything that had to do with not treating
animals properly because she really loves her dog and whatever. But anyway,
so every time there would be like a גמרא Gemara that would
be really problematic, right, I would start in terms of our sensibilities,
I'd start hemming and hawing and trying to explain it, and I
just remember she said, Rabbi Linzer, it is not your responsibility to
like, you know, to make the גמרא Gemara be okay. She says,
but what, you know, the problem is
is that if we try to smooth it over, then we're not
acknowledging, right, the problematics of it, and we're allowing, and therefore we're
being, and therefore she said, and you know, and she's right, of
course the biggest problem is places where it's taught where you don't
highlight. You don't have to come up with an answer. But if
you don't acknowledge the problem, then it, then you just internalize this
sense, oh, so killing a non-Jew is not really so bad. Stealing
from a non-Jew is fundamentally permissible. You know, and that is the
big problem. The big problem is is that when we don't sort
of, you know, in all the places, exactly as you said, all
the ישיבות yeshivas and all the places where it gets taught without
being problematized, you know? And look, these גמרות Gemaras are quoted by
some rabbis in Israel, you know, relating to some very practical political
issues and attitudes, whatever. You know, it's not just theoretical. So it
really is a deep issue. All right. Anyway, so moving on. Okay.
So where were we? כיוצא בו. kayotze bo. Now, מה כיוצא בו
בגזל מהי? ma kayotze bo b'gezel mahi? When we say, oh, גזל
gezel includes similar things. What do we mean by similar things? אמר
רב אחא בר יעקב, amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov, לא נצרכה אלא
לפועל בכרם. lo nitzrecha ela le'poel bekerem. A worker in a vine,
that they are not, now, he is not allowed to take from
the grapes as he is, as he is working. So the גמרא
Gemara says one minute. פועל בכרם אימת? poel bekerem eimat? At what
period, at what stage? אי בשעת גמר מלאכה, ei besha'at gmar melacha,
if it's when it's harvesting at the end of the process, harvesting
the grapes, היתרא הוא. heteira hu. It's permitted. Now, how do we
know it's permitted? Because it's permitted for a Jew. And just because
it's permitted for a Jew, it means it's permitted for a non-Jew?
Like, you know, it's a very fascinating question. Is this based on
a principle that we're going to see later that the גמרא Gemara
says that there can't be something that's permissible for a Jew that's
forbidden for a non-Jew? Like there's got to be an assumption that,
you know, since we have 613 מצוות, mitzvos, we're obviously, you know,
our, you know, at least as restrictive as, you know, as the
שבע מצוות. sheva mitzvos. It has to be more restrictive. Can't be
more lenient. Maybe. But of course in issues by the way of
whether he's allowed to take or not, I don't know if it's
restrictive or not restrictive. It's like you're allowing, you know, it's nice
to the worker, it's not nice to the, you know, it's not
nice to the owner. I mean, the owner has to give something
up. It's not clear to me like which is the more... harsher
rule, but it seems also that a way of reading it is
not the comparison of Jew to non-Jew, but the גמרא's Gemara's understanding
that there's something like deep, the fact that by a Jewish worker,
you're allowed to eat when they do the work, you know, reflects
some somehow deep sense of like, that there's a fundamental, like an
animal even you don't muzzle. You know, some deep sense that that's
like, that there's a natural right to do that, to not restrain
somebody from doing that, not even restraining an animal. So presumably if
that has to be permissible by non-Jews as well. So it's really
fascinating the גמרא Gemara understands that it's permissible by Jews it's gotta
be permissible by non-Jews. Why is that? Is that based again on
this comparison that Jews have to be at least as strict as
non-Jews or is it based on like some understanding that there's some
deep right to be doing this? Anyway, so אי בשעת גמר מלאכה,
ei b'shaas gmar melacha, היתירה הוא. hetira hu. It's permissible. אי לא
בשעת גמר מלאכה, ei lo b'shaas gmar melacha, and if it's eating
from the food when they're not doing that final act, so גזל
מעליא הוא. gezel maalya hu. So it's real theft. So it's not
כיוצא בו. k'yotze bo. It's just a straight theft. So of course
it's not the way a lot of people think, you know, oh,
stealing from my work supply closet, that's not real theft. Okay. So
it's like, no, you don't need an extra thing in the ברייתא
braisa to teach you that. That's real theft whether you think it
is or not. אלא אמר רב פפא, ela amar Rav Pappa, לא
נצרכא אלא לפחות משוה פרוטה, lo nitzrecha ela l'pachos mishaveh prutah, less
than a penny. Okay. א פרוטה a prutah is actually probably less
than a penny, but anyway, even less than what we would consider
to be the minimum denomination, less than a penny which we would
consider to be not even real money, that is included. You combine
those two, so a non-Jew steals less than a penny and they're
חייב מיתה. chayav misa. All right, anyway, so that's why it's a
חידוש, chiddush, even less than a penny. אי הכי, ei hachi, says
the גמרא, Gemara, כותי בישראל אסור? Kuti b'Yisrael assur? So then why
when a non-Jew steals from ישראל Yisrael less than a שוה פרוטה,
shaveh prutah, is that אסור? assur? Why not? הא בר מחילה הוא.
ha bar mechila hu. A Jew will be מוחל. machel. So this
is interesting. The גמרא Gemara assumes that the reason less than א
פרוטה a prutah is different between Jew and non-Jew initially is that
Jews are nice guys. So you steal less than a penny from
me I say, eh, forget it, מוחל. machel. But non-Jews, you steal
less than a penny from them and they're not going to be
מוחל. machel. They're going to be wanting their half-penny back. Right, it's
like the exact reverse stereotype, okay? All right, I'll just stop there
one. What's the purpose, you know, what's the goal
of Jewish football? Anybody know? To get the quarterback. So anyway, okay.
Okay, so anyway, moving on. Okay, so here I just had to
balance something out here.
Anyway, so, and I mean who steals less than a penny?
A quarter's real money, right? Exactly, exactly. Anyway, all right, so the
non-Jew won't be מוחל machel the less than a penny, the Jew
will. But wait, but then why when a non-Jew steals from a
Jew, should he transgress? Because the Jew will be מוחל machel the
less than the penny. So the גמרא Gemara says, so that's
true, מיהא בתר הכי מוחל. miha basar hachi machel. It's true, after
it's stolen, the Jew will say, אה מוחל, ah machel, don't give
it back. But צערא בשעתיה מיהא איתא. tzara b'shaita miha ita. At
the moment of theft, you took something from the person. There was
a sense of like, you know, of like, you know, of invading
the person, taking something away. That was an act of theft, even
if the person is willing to be מוחל machel it immediately. Okay?
And therefore for them that's included in theft. Of course the question
is,
so wait a minute, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, כותי
דכותי כיוצא בהן. Kuti d'Kuti k'yotze bahen. Wait a minute, says the
גמרא, Gemara, but if that's so, why would you have to tell
me, oh, from a non-Jew,
not even like classic theft, even things that are similar, you're also
transgressing? So the גמרא Gemara says a non-Jew against a non-Jew, that's
not just related, that's actual theft. כיון דלאו בני מחילה נינהו גזל
מעליא הוא. kevan d'lav bnei mechila ninhu gezel maalya hu. Since they're
not like, you know, of the type that would be מוחל, machel,
for them a penny and less than a penny doesn't matter. So
on the one hand, less than a penny from a Jew is
a חידוש, chiddush, that you might have thought that that's not גזל
gezel because the Jew is מוחל. machel. But the גמרא Gemara is
saying from a non-Jew from a non-Jew less than a penny, that's
not כיוצא בו. k'yotze bo. Since they're not מוחל, machel, less than
a penny is just the same as a penny and it's all
the same. Now we have to pause for a moment and say
like, okay, but like why then a Jew from a Jew less
than a penny, like even if they're מוחל, machel, why isn't that
the same transgression? And also like why is this punishable by death?
It seems very harsh. So let me, I mean, as it all
seems harsh if it's all punishable by death. But anyway, let me
just give you an analogy which might sound a little shocking but
it helps explain it. If somebody wounds another person, so what's, you
know, breaks their arm, what's their liability? They have all these financial
liabilities, right? To pay for the doctor bill and to pay for
the injury and all those types of things. Let's say somebody wounds,
do they get any other punishment other than financial? No. Let's say
somebody wounds another person. type of a wound that's less than a
פרוטה. prutah. Less than a—I can't even imagine what that would be,
but a type of a wound that the financial payment for it
would be less than a פרוטה. prutah. Do you know what you
do to the person? He doesn't pay any money, but you give
him lashes because he transgressed the prohibition of wounding a fellow person.
So the question is, well, why not give everybody lashes? No, because
in cases where you're talking about paying money, we focus on the
restitution, not on the punishment. But when there is no restitution, we
focus on the punishment and on the lashes. So therefore, what רש"י,
Rashi, the way רש"י Rashi explains it is that when a Jew
steals, by a Jew, what does it say? It says, if you
steal, והשיב את הגזילה. vehashivata hagezeilah. The focus is restitution. Since the
focus is restitution, therefore, it's always about paying the money back. Now,
you would say, so why not, if I steal less than a
פרוטה, prutah, shouldn't I get lashes? Okay, so there it's even worse,
it's even different than the wounding case. There, the whole focus—by wounding,
I've actually injured you, and that stands by itself, forgetting what I've
taken away from you. But by theft, it all focuses on the
aspect of what you've lost, right? And therefore, it's all about restitution.
That's for Jews, and therefore there's only the payment. But for non-Jews,
it's not about restitution; there's no paying back. So it's all just
about punishment for the act. So therefore, and since for them, more
than a פרוטה, prutah, less than a פרוטה prutah doesn't matter, for
them it's all considered to be this one punishment of the death
penalty. So I don't know if that helps or not, but at
least it explains a type of a structure it fits into. For
them, there's no line between penny and less than a penny; for
us, there is the line. With the penny, it's about restitution, and
without, even less than a פרוטה, prutah, since fundamentally the whole thing
is about property and restitution from this perspective, from the Jewish perspective,
then there's no consequence by less than a פרוטה. prutah. Yes.
Do you know, is there anything about like not dealing with realities
here that makes them more like as you're saying, or the Gil
thing's also, meaning like they're not imagining an actual situation where
we're going to judge a non-Jew for stealing less than a פרוטה
prutah and putting the non-Jew to death? Right, so that is true,
meaning it does allow them to develop, you know,
an—like, again, this is the book I mentioned I'm going to have
to find a time to bring into some of what her insights
in her book, Deborah Steinmetz, but you know, on her book on
this, what she calls it, like so much of סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, she
says, is an ideal world—ideal in the sense of not perfect world,
but like ideation, you know, imagine like what should—you know, so like
we're creating this structure, not necessarily this is actually how it's being
implemented. And even more so than
the
most, maybe we will have a סנהדרין Sanhedrin again, right? Right. Right,
like, do we imagine—right, well, we could imagine us judging non-Jews in
the land of Israel that we have, you know, I mean, that's
what we have nowadays, right? All
right, let's try to just read a little bit of my notes.
Already 8:30, but let's try to read a little bit more, maybe
we'll even turn the page. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא—so ella anyway, we don't need less than a פרוטה, prutah, that
would be normal גזל. gezel. אלא אמר רב אחא בריה דרב איקא
לא נצרכה אלא לכובש שכר
שכיר—holding Ella amar Rav Acha bar Brei deRav Ika lo nitzrecha ela
koves sachar sachir back a worker's wages. So that's interesting. That's not
גזל gezel in the sense that you're not actively taking away; you're
just passively not giving, not giving something that they deserve. So you
know, for a Jew also, the גמרא Gemara in בבא מציעא Bava
Metzia says that you transgress לא תגזול, lo tigzol, or whatever, but
it's a חידוש chiddush that you transgress לא תגזול lo tigzol because—okay,
so that's part of, that's also included here. Okay, now, כותי בכותי
וכותי בישראל אסור ישראל בכותי מותר. kusei bekusei vekusei beYisrael assur Yisrael
bekusei mutar.
Okay, we're back to that. Okay, for Jew versus a non-Jew, that
gets, by the way, even those that say that stealing from a
non-Jew is forbidden, you know, there's a position that not paying them
what you owe them, הפקעת הלוואתו, hapkavat halvata,
is permissible, and that's essentially כובש שכר שכיר. koves sachar sachir. So
again, we're not here to deal with all those problematics about גזל
גוי; gezel goy; that's the גמרא Gemara in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma.
כיוצא בו—כיוצא בו ביפת תואר מאי? Now since it said similar things,
so we got to similar for theft is not paying wages. What's
similar to יפת תואר, yifat toar, which remember is still in the
context here of a type of a theft? So כי אתא רב
דימי אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי חנינא—בן נח שיחד שפחה shifcha לעבדו
ובא עליה נהרג עליה. neherag aleha. So if a Noachide designated a
שפחה for his servant, for his slave, so it's not a question
of עריות arayot because there's no marriage for slaves. So and then
he went ahead and he had intercourse with her, which is a
way of taking her away, so it's not like stealing a woman
away from her country in war, but taking this woman away from
a man to whom she's designated without it being עריות arayot because
they're not married, נהרג עליה. neherag aleha, So that would be that
case about נהרג עליה, that would be כיוצא בו. Keyotzei bo Of
course, the other problematics here, in addition to all the Jew-non-Jew distinctions,
is you know, woman as man's property. Like, so designated this woman
to this man is a type of a stealing from the
man. כיוצא בו בשפיכות דמים לא תניא. Keyotzei bo deshvichat damim lo
tanya. Now we had כיוצא בו keyotzei bo. by גזל; gezel; we
didn't have כיוצא בו... keyotzei bo by murder. So it sounds like
there are no peripheral cases of murder. It either is murder or
isn't murder. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אמר אביי אי משתכחת
דתניא Amar Abaye i mishtakchat detanya but it's very fascinating. We're like
filling in a vacuum here. If you ever find somebody that says
oh there are some כיוצא בו keyotzei bo... cases of murder that
a non-Jew would be liable for, רב יונתן בן שאול Rav Yonatan
ben Shaul it's רב יונתן בן שאול. Rav Yonatan ben Shaul.
It's a great name by the way, יונתן בן שאול. Yonatan ben
Shaul. Okay, דתניא detanya we taught in
a
ברייתא, Baraita, רב יונתן בן שאול אומר Rav Yonatan ben Shaul omer
רודף אחר חבירו להרגו יכול להצילו באחד מאיבריו ולא הצילו. Rodef achar
chaveiro lehorgo yachol lehatzilo be'achad me'eivarav velo hitzilo. Somebody was running after
somebody trying to kill him, so you have a right to self-defense.
So you killed the guy who was pursuing you, but you could
have stopped him by, you know, by shooting him in the arm,
and instead you actually killed the guy. And now of course it's
always very, what do you mean יכול להצילו באחד מאיבריו? yachol lehatzilo
be'achad me'eivarav? Like you gotta, you know, you usually don't have the
frame of mind or whatever to think that somebody, you know, often
people do what they have to do to make sure they've removed
the threat. You know, what could you say 'well you could have
done otherwise', but sometimes they could have. Anyway, so here's the question:
if it's assessed... was this on...?
it might have come up before. Anyway, it definitely comes up a
couple places in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, later it's definitely going to come up.
Anyway, if it's assessed that the person could have stopped the threat
without killing the other person, then that is considered to be נהרג
עליו. neherag alav. According to this, this is even a Jew and
a Jew as well. Okay? This is not a Jew non-Jew distinction.
Okay? Is that what happened...
just to keep... just to kill the Palestinian?
Yeah, exactly. Right, that's after he was neutralized, right. So it's one
thing after the threat's been neutralized, but when somebody's still feeling under
the threat, to be able to say, 'well, you could have done
something else', right, I mean that's
also part of the IDF's like, you know, that they have to
shoot up or they have to shoot... right, exactly. So at what
stage is it judged that somebody had a reasonable
alternative? And at what stage is it judged like, you know,
they didn't? So that's always a question, but here it is: if
it's judged that they had a reasonable alternative, then actually and that
would be a הלכה halacha even for Jews, that you would be
executed. So that would also apply to non-Jews. That would be the
כיוצא בו. kiyozei bo It's not straight-out murder, okay, but if it's
assessed that the person could have neutralized the threat otherwise and he
did it by killing the person, then again, whether Jew or whether
non-Jew, according to this approach... not everybody agrees. Some say obviously you
try to stop them by one limb, but if you actually kill
them it's not murder, right, it's self-defense. But according to this approach
that says that it is murder in that case, that would be
the כיוצא בו. kiyozei bo. By the way, and with this we'll
end for now, I want to say another interesting thing is, is
that which shouldn't have been taken for granted, is that you could
have said how do I know that the permission... this is always
a fun thing like that they talk about, you know, that the
פוסקים Poskim talk about. How do I know that the same permissions
that apply to a Jew apply to a non-Jew? So a Jew
is allowed
to self-defend and to kill the person who's coming after him. How
do I know that's allowed for a non-Jew? A non-Jew is prohibited
in murder. How do I know that they have the permission of
self-defense? Well, this גמרא Gemara makes it clear that they do. But
there's other interesting questions like for example, like a Jew is supposed
to do one of the, you know,
do a sin rather than give up his life. What about a
non-Jew? Somebody holds a gun to a non-Jew's head and says steal
or I'll kill you. Are they supposed to martyr themselves or say
the opposite? Maybe a non-Jew doesn't even have to martyr himself for
עבודה זרה, גילוי עריות ושפיכות דמים. avodah zarah, giluy arayos, ushfichus damim.
Maybe he has no obligation of martyrdom. Like so when some of
these... how do some of the sort of parameters, you know, within
how these מצוות mitzvos play out among Jews, the limits and the
overrides, how does that play out within the context of שבע מצוות
בני נח? Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach? That becomes a fun area to
explore. Okay, we'll end for now.